A Guide to the Kappa Kappa Psi Records, 1958-2009 (bulk 1979-2009): UA 0021
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Kappa Kappa Psi Records,
1958-2009 (bulk 1979-2009)
Special Collections, James Madison University
Kappa Kappa Psi
UA 0021
5.86 Cubic Feet; 14 boxes
The Kappa Kappa Psi Records, 1958-2009 (bulk 1979-2009), contain organizational files of and pertaining to the Eta Omicron chapter of the band service fraternity Kappa Kappa Psi at James Madison University. In addition to these administrative files is a large collection of photographic and ephemeral material.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated to Special Collections by Kappa Kappa Psi in April 2016.
Administrative History
Kappa Kappa Psi, along with its sister organization Tau Beta Sigma, is a national service fraternity dedicated to providing logistical and organizational support for college and university bands. It was founded on the Oklahoma State University campus in 1919. The organization currently is active on over 200 college and university campuses and consists of 5,000 active members annually.
The Eta Omicron chapter of Kappa Kappa Psi at James Madison University was initiated in 1979 to assist with the recently formed Marching Royal Dukes. The group was petitioned for colonization by the director of the Marching Royal Dukes, Mike Davis, in March of 1979. The first chapter officers included Ken Langer as president and Tom McKenzie as vice president. The colony was officially initiated and installed on November 9, 1980, becoming the 183rd chapter of the fraternity. Since Eta Omicron's founding, it has served as advising chapter to Theta Psi at Virginia Union University, Iota Xi at Norfolk State University, Kappa Theta at Liberty University, Zeta Psi at Virginia State University, Beta Chi at the University of Virginia, and Mu Nu at Christopher Newport University.
The Eta Omicron chapter is open for membership to anyone who has or is currently participating in a JMU band program, including Marching Royal Dukes, Brass Band, Concert Band, Symphonic Band, or Wind Symphony. Rush events occur in both fall and spring semesters. Over the course of its existence, Kappa Kappa Psi has worked alongside Tau Beta Sigma to provide services to the Marching Royal Dukes. These services include pre-rehearsal field setup, uniform cleaning, instrument transportation, event preparation, pre-season mailing, and fund raising. These efforts take place year-round for the preparation and maintenance of the marching band. Other duties expected of members include actively participating in a university ensemble, maintaining a 2.0 GPA, maintaining annual dues, ushering at least one university concert per semester, and attending all required meetings.
Scope and Content
The Kappa Kappa Psi Records, 1958-2009 (bulk 1979-2009), consists of 5.86 cubic feet of material stored in 14 boxes. The collections consists primarily of organizational files and photographs that pertain to the Eta Omicron chapter of Kappa Kappa Psi. The collection also includes assorted ephemeral material as well as a series of annual scrapbooks.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 5 series:
Series 1: Organizational Files, 1983-2007
Series 2: Ephemera, 1958-1989
Series 3: Photographs, 1979-2006
Series 4: Scrapbooks and Albums, 1979-2005
Series 5: Oversize, 1989-2001
Series 1 and Series 2 are arranged alphabetically by topic. Series 3 is arranged by form then chronologically. Series 4 is arranged chronologically. Series 5 is arranged by size.
Related Material
Marching Royal Dukes Records, 1975-2016, SC 0016, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
Bibliography
"Who is KKPsi?" https://www.kkpsi.org/about/who-is-kappa-kappa-psi/ (Accessed June 2017).
"Eta Omicron Chapter History." https://jmukkpsi.wordpress.com/about/eta-omicron/history/ (Accessed June 2017).
"Kappa Kappa Psi." https://www.jmu.edu/mrd/kappakappapsi.shtml (Accessed June 2017).
"Tau Beta Sigma." https://www.jmu.edu/mrd/taubetasigma.shtml (Accessed June 2017).
Index Terms
Subjects:
James Madison University. Marching Royal Dukes; Kappa Kappa Psi; Madison College -- Students; James Madison University -- Students; Madison College -- History; James Madison University -- History; Greek letter societies -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Student activities -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Music students -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- Social life and customs
Genre and Form Terms:
Administrative reports; Letters (correspondence); Administrative records; Printed Ephemera; Photographs; Color slides; Color negatives; Scrapbooks; Photograph albums
- Series 1: Organizational Files, 1983-2009
  Scope and Content
  Series 1: Organizational Files, 1983-2009, consists primarily of documentation of events, members, and general administrative files used by the Eta Omicron chapter of Kappa Kappa Psi. The majority of these files are institutional guidelines and activity reports to and from the national chapter of Kappa Kappa Psi. Such guiding files include the organizational constitutions, as well as event-specific handbooks.
  Interesting material within the series include the multiple folders of advising material provided to the Eta Omicron chapter throughout its history. The advising material consists primarily of correspondence between the national chapter and Eta Omicron, as well as between Eta Omicrons and the chapters being advised. This series also includes activity reports and copies of pledge information from advisee chapters. There are also multiple sources of material on providing guidelines for advising chapters and beginning their path to full membership. The advising files include those for the Liberty University colony, Norfolk State chapter, and Virginia State University chapter.
  Other interesting material includes the member lists, family trees, and record roll books. These materials provide several instances of well-recorded names of members and their corresponding pledge families. The roll books also provide a look into the level of involvement certain members took in the organization, as all meetings were recorded and logged between 1990-2000 and 2006-2007.
  - Activity and Summary Reports, 1987-2006, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitutions and Guides, 1985-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1983-2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Kappa Kappa Psi Newsletter, 1992-2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Liberty University Colonization Material (folder 1 of 2), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Liberty University Colonization Material (folder 2 of 2), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Members and Family Trees, 1993-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Convention 1999 Bid Material (folder 1 of 2), 1991-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - National Convention 1999 Bid Material (folder 2 of 2), 1991-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Norfolk State Advising Material, 1989-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Parliamentary Guidelines, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Record Roll Book, 1990-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Record Roll Book, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Rush and Pledge Material, 1985-2003, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Virginia State University Advising Material (folder 1 of 2), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Virginia State University Advising Material (folder 2 of 2), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Ephemera, 1958-1989
  Series 2: Ephemera, 1958-1989, consists primarily of loose ephemeral material found scattered throughout the collection. The majority of this material is stored in Assorted Ephemera, made up of various pamphlets on Kappa Kappa Psi, JMU musical programs, and certificates of recognition for the Eta Omicron chapter.
  The Iota and Eta pledge bios are self-written biographies of the members of the Iota and Eta pledge classes. These bios go into detail about their town of origin as well as their interest and involvement in music and band. The bio for David Greenanagel of the Eta pledge class is written after his graduation and details his importance to later members of the organization. The Kyle Langer cassette has an original song recording from 1987 by Kappa Kappa Psi member Kyle Langer.
  - Assorted Ephemera, 1958-1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Iota and Eta Pledge Bios, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Kyle Langer Cassette, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 3: Photographs, 1979-2006
  Series 3: Photographs, 1979-2006, represents the bulk of the collection. The series consist of photographic material of and pertaining to the Eta Omicron chapter of Kappa Kappa Psi. The photographs begin with the chapter's creation in 1979 to 2006.
  The majority of the photographs portray the members of the Eta Omicron chapter participating in group events or providing services to the Marching Royal Dukes. There are also scattered photographs of the Marching Royal Dukes in performance at assorted events and football games. Instances of these photographic topics are represented in nearly every year, including the undated photographs.
  Also included are candid photographs spanning nearly every year represented in the series. The candid photographs portray the Kappa Kappa Psi members, often with Tau Beta Sigma members, relaxing in personal apartments, giving a look into student off-campus life. Several photographs are taken inside apartments in The Mill Apartments complex in Harrisonburg, a traditional off-campus living location for Kappa Kappa Psi, Tau Beta Sigma, and Marching Royal Dukes members.
  Negatives and slides are stored in their original envelopes or cases where applicable for organizational purposes.
  - Photographs, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (folder 1 of 2), 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs (folder 2 of 2), 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (folder 1 of 2), 1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs (folder 2 of 2), 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photographs (folder 1 of 2), 1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (folder 2 of 2), 1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photographs (folder 1 of 4), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (folder 2 of 4), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (folder 3 of 4), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (folder 4 of 4), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (folder 1 of 4), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (folder 2 of 4), undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (folder 3 of 4), undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (folder 4 of 4), undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Slides, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Negatives (folder 1 of 7), 1979-2006 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Negatives (folder 2 of 7), 1979-2006 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Negatives (folder 3 of 7), 1979-2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Negatives (folder 4 of 7), 1979-2006 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Negatives (folder 5 of 7), 1979-2006 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Negatives (folder 6 of 7), 1979-2006 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Negatives (folder 7 of 7), 1979-2006 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Series 4: Scrapbooks and Albums, 1979-2005
  Series 4: Scrapbooks and Albums, 1979-2005, consists of the annual Kappa Kappa Psi scrapbooks from 1979-2005. These scrapbooks consist of photographic and written information on the events and activities that were best-received by the members of the Eta Omicron chapter on an annual basis. Common topics included the "smoker" events, pledge classes, formal events, and assorted service events that members participated in. Some albums include lists of names and examples of family trees, such as the 1996 photo album and the Family Tree Scrapbook represented in the Oversize series.
  - Scrapbook, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1990-1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Album, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Series 5: Oversize, 1989-2001
  Series 5: Oversize, 1989-2001, consists of materials that do not fit within standard sized boxes and have been physically removed from their intellectual arrangement. As such, the Oversize series functions only as a container list. The following folder titles are each represented elsewhere in the collection, exclusively the scrapbooks series. These materials are arranged by size to facilitate ease of access.
  - Scrapbook, 1989 (Box OV 1, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1989-1990 (Box OV 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1990 (Box OV 1, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1992-1993 (Box OV 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1996 (Box OV 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1997 (Box OV 2, Folder 2)
  - Family Tree Scrapbook, undated (Box OV 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 2001 (Box OV 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1997-1998 (Box OV 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1998-1999 (Box OV 3, Folder 3)